Hello! The Web3 bug I will show you today is
absolutely insane! Almost like I could tell you
to give me some money and it would be directly
transferred from your wallet to mine. That's
why the bounty for it was the equivalent of $1
mln. And we'll have the bug explained to us by
someone with way better Web3 skills than I - lead
offensive security engineer from Halborn - Michał
Bajor. Enjoy! Hello Michał, thank you so much
for joining me to explain the bug. The bug
was in the process of exchanging the tokens.
Different kinds of tokens. Could you talk us
through what tokens were they? Sure, hi Greg,
thanks for having me. Well, basically you have
Near-specific tokens which are are called NEP-141
compatibles and then you have ERC20 tokens which
exist in the Aurora blockchain that implements
basically an Ethereum-like network. And you have
a token on the Near side and you want to transfer
it to the Aurora. There is a process for this and
the vulnerability we'll be talking about is was
found exactly in this process. So could you show
us the code? How did it look like normally,
without messing up things yet? Absolutely!
NEP-141 tokens on the Near side are specific
because they contain an ft_transfer_call
function which performs a similar thing as an
ERC20 approval but with one transaction. It
essentially means that you are transferring
some tokens and with this transfer, you want
to call some function in some other contract.
In this case, you would use this function the
ft_transfer_call on a token that you want to
send to the Aurora. And specify that it should,
that this token should call Aurora contract in
the process. And this is standardized and in this
case, the ft_on_transfer function will actually be
called which is the case here. And well basically,
there are arguments provided to this this call one
of it is a message. That will be very important
soon but if everything goes smoothly, then you
go into the receive erc20 tokens in the Aurora
contract. And this function looks like this. You
basically parse this message that you have here
but let me show you the vulnerable code actually,
and not the one that that contains the fixes.
There are ERC-20 tokens. It parses this message
that's contained within the arguments because this
message contains information about the recipient
address and this is the address of the recipient
on the Aurora Network and information about
any fee that this person needs to pay for
this transaction. And this fee might of course be
zero. You parse it and then you check. Basically,
the first 40 characters are related
to the recipient and if there is something after
those characters, then this will be considered as
a fee that must be paid. If this fee is not zero,
in this case, you basically... Is this fee
the same when I do a transaction via Metamask,
there is a pop-up about a fee of the transaction.
Is this fee the same or does is this something
different? This is not the same fee although they
are related. The fee you're talking about is just
the fee associated with sending a transaction
and you still need to pay this fee here. But
you will be paying for in the Near side, not in
the Aurora. And this fee was designed by Aurora
team for the cases where users would like to send
tokens from the Rainbow Bridge to the Aurora and
they wouldn't have the Near tokens, sorry, Near
account ID. Like they wouldn't basically be using
Near blockchain. They just would like to use the
Aurora chain. However, it was actually never used
like this. Aurora relayer is you sending those
transactions to Aurora so users don't actually
need to need to pay for them. However, in
general that's the fee for for those cases
because they they wouldn't be able to pay
the Near transaction fee because they don't
use Near so maybe they should pay some fee on the
Aurora side in the Ether that's already on the Aurora.
So if I would be sending some tokens to you
then I decide what fee you should pay, right?
Yes and this is the core of the of the
vulnerability here because as you can see here,
both the recipient and the fee are encoded in the
message and the message is one of the arguments
provided within the transaction. This is fully in
the control of whoever is sending the transaction
which means that it's fully in control of the
attacker. So attacker chooses who will receive
the tokens and how much fee that person will
need to pay. So you can basically just make it
a highest value possible and still Ether from that
person, although there are some limitations to it.
What are the limitations? Could I steal all your
money? Yes, you could you can but not in a single
transaction. In the single transaction,
you actually are limited to the 18.4 Ether
transfer. And that's because although the fee is
parsed from the message that's 64 characters long
and it's parsed into the uint256 type then within
the transfer, it's actually casted as an unsigned
integer of 64 bits length which is way smaller.
And if you would provide something that doesn't
fit into this 64 bits, then it would basically...
The rust will panic and the whole transaction
would fail so we would just need to provide um a
smaller number. But then you can just execute the
attack multiple times and still drain the funds
of your target. And considering that apart from
getting the fee, I have to send you something,
how much value have to be the tokens that I
send to you? Absolutely nothing! You can...
That's the very interesting part because this
Aurora is permissionless and it is very easy to
create your own tokens in the Aurora and create
the mapping between them - between the token
on the Near site and the token on the in the
Aurora. Anyone can do it without any additional
authorization. So imagine a scenario that I create
a meaningless token that I just will deploy
to the Near blockchain. Then, I create one in
the Aurora, I map between them which I can
do in a single transaction in the Aurora,
and then I send you some tokens in the Aurora
and say that you need to pay for them 18.4
ether. For the tokens that mean nothing to you
and probably to anyone else. And I have no way
of preventing this, right? No you don't, no you
don't. This is the core of this vulnerability.
So how was this fixed? Did they introduce some
kind of verification for me to to confirm the
transaction? Yeah, well, as I mentioned in the
regular operation, this fee was actually never
not zero which made it actually quite easy to fix
this vulnerability because... Let me show you the
fixed code. The the Aurora team basically just
manually set the fee to be zero at all times.
This is just a quick fix but then, later, in
the newest version, you will not see fee at all
in this in function. In this function, it was
completely removed from the execution process.
So is there any meaningful recommendation you
could give to any developers to not make such
a mistake? It seems quite stupid to me if I'm
honest. Yes, it does because this was a flaw in on
the design level. Basically, as a rule of thumb,
in blockchain and probably not only in blockchain,
if user didn't agree explicitly to something,
don't make him pay for anything. So if,
for instance, if this transaction would require
the receiver to also sign this transaction somehow
and explicitly say that they agreed to to receive
the tokens, then in that case there may be some
scenario where this sort of mechanism would be
meaningful. But basically, as a rule of thumb,
the person who's paying
for anything should be only the one who sends
the transaction. Okay, thank you so much for for
explaining the bug. I'm happy that it's it's been
fixed and I hope that as a whitehat, we will not
see many of such mistakes done again. Oh, yeah,
me too, for sure! If you want to see the video
that was the world's largest bounty to date,
check out this one on your screen right now
about the vulnerability in Polygon blockchain.
For now, thank you for watching and goodbye!